good sneeze
um
so
then relax your forehead
and relax the corners of your mouth
relax your eyelids
relax your fingers
little smile
try to keep that smile
and then come to your breath
um
long exhales
uh
then please invite your heart teacher to
come sit in front of you
could be
someone from the past
historical
teacher
or someone you knew earlier in your life
could be someone you haven't met yet
the perfect teacher for you
or it could be someone that we are
fortunate to have in our life now
and let them come sit
with you
quiet
and
peaceful
and enjoyable
so
then bow down to them by thinking
of something
you really like about them
you can tell them in your heart what it
is
then make them an offering maybe
i think it's very very
good offering
to offer the three-day retreat you did
so those retreats are very very
important in your life it's good if you
can do
at least two or three per year
a weekend or five days
offer that
beautiful practice to your teacher
so
uh
then
[Music]
open up your heart
to your teacher almost literally
split it open
and
show them something you're not so happy
about about yourself
some bad habit you have
ask them to help you get over this
so
then think of some good habit you
haven't
tell your momma
thank them
and
really
try to
enjoy this good side of yourself this
good part
it's
important
uh
then ask your teacher to teach
you
share with you
at the same time
appreciating that they are coming from
you
and you will have to share with others
to have a good teacher
so
and then ask them to stay in your life
influencing me for the better
uh
then i'd like you to think about
something you would like to achieve in
your life
during the next month
during may
may is a beautiful time
in most parts of the world
of new beginnings spring
and think of some change you'd like to
make in your life
or some goal you'd like to reach
personally i have this dream of
making more time
to do the things i want to do
i would it's not that i feel nervous or
pressure i just wouldn't like to do more
things i'd
like to
time to
slow down a little bit
have more time during the day
to do the many things i enjoy
so try to decide on
some goal for the next
month
could be a negative goal could be
i'm having
trouble getting along with this person
i would like to
by the end of the month i'd like to be
their friend something like that
ugh
angry
so
then
consciously
take refuge
decide oh
i will take refuge to reach my goal
i will take refuge too
to solve this problem i have
and
and really refugees
deciding that
this thing you want or this thing you
want to improve
is empty
it's not going to be
one way or the other by itself
it's not going to happen
it's gonna follow your sins
so
then make a little plan in your mind
four steps always for steps
about
achieving this dream huh
so take take
get slow
just relax your body park your body
go through the four steps though
sometimes i think we don't even have
time to think about them
and make a little plan for yourself
for
when you
go home
from this beautiful place
and what
how how am i going to take refuge by
using the four steps
for this
dream i have
for
may
the month of may
so
uh
don't forget to
plan your
coffee meditation
in the evening
from the month of may
it's a good way to fall asleep
thinking about good things
you've done
helpful for other people
didn't ask your llama to come to your
heart you you know what to do
bring them
down your
central channel
and bring them into a tiny
globe
crystal globe the size
of a grain of sugar in your heart
so
then please come back to your breath
three long breaths three long exhales
don't open your eyes yet
then you can open your eyes take a
stretch
um
ugh
hmm
[Music]
all right
uh
we have some schedule changes
it
it's still windy
and uh looks like it's gonna be windy
into the evening and uh
so we had an idea
uh i've never done a fire pooja in the
morning
[Music]
uh i thought it might be nice
so uh
we're gonna do one at six o'clock
tomorrow morning
uh
and you can come or you can sleep okay
if you come you're going to be grumpy on
the plane that's okay
just don't take
united and then that's my airline by the
way
i'm super super duper diamond gold
status
anyway they treat me nice
sometimes
so uh
six o'clock tomorrow morning okay uh
same place
out here uh we'll have snacks there okay
we'll have some kind of breakfast stuff
there okay
and uh
you don't have to
be at attention the whole time
you know you can just walk around and
you know eat some
scrambled eggs and
okay
and enjoy
uh
maybe we just served the breakfast here
okay
in the jets and carpet center you can
come and go
okay
to the puja
and
but there's a
black male we have to make a deal
i need 10 people at five o'clock
actually twelve
two do it
so
chinzone stand up
write get a piece of paper write these
names down
[Music]
five o'clock
it's still dark
uh
to help get the puja ready
okay
12 12 people
i need at least three boys
to carry heavy stuff
well words were three boys
i guess chinson wants you to sign the
paper
if you're a boy put a check mark
okay
yes ma'am
ask the dime mountain staff
[Music]
sounds good
uh we're doing all this planning without
melissa and michael right
i hope they don't mind
so breakfast should be available from
about
seven o'clock
so people can just walk over and eat and
come back to the fire okay then we don't
try to do all that
around the fire it's too messy
okay
then today
um
aaron where's erin
i'm not supposed am i doing yoga today
no
yeah
so am i doing yoga no
i'm kidding
jb
okay good
oh great
it works out
uh so
i'm gonna do yoga hooky
and uh
me and adam
okay
10 30 casita
and uh nick
and
erin you can
come
in tyrone where's
he tyrone over rock-and-rolled him
yesterday
uh
i need him too yeah
the thing we were trying to do last
night
because we have to do it for the spirits
in the morning
okay
and uh michael
so we need that stuff at uh
10 30
after this class
and uh
two two or three boys to help michael
we'll work it out
okay
all right don't forget at 12 15 we have
a waffle eating contest
for everybody who made a donation so
please try to make your donation before
12 15.
what else we have a nice debate for you
today four o'clock
okay
me and the team debate team
uh
if you're on the diamond mountain or aci
board
we have a meeting at 5 45
okay
uh it's diamond mountain for half an
hour and then
but we don't have a combined meaning or
something like that
not necessary
okay diamond mountain board uh 545
and if you come you get dinner
okay and then the rest of schedule is
what it was supposed to be so whatever
your schedule says is still correct
tomorrow
you know early fire present
okay
and you don't have to come you know if
you feel stressed out packing and
you're tired and
you don't have to come it's just for fun
okay
and don't forget to
wear a hat
put on sunscreen
wear sunglasses okay
and if you feel too hot or uncomfortable
you can come
in here and eat some more and then go
back
daniel has a question
we have an idea
oh
and and we determined we decided me and
chenzon if it's really windy we'll just
offer the stuff anyway
without the fire
and then our friends
will be happy with that
the wild pigs okay
by the way they're really cute and they
have very powerful teeth so
don't try to pet them okay
i mean
don't don't bother them in the desert
everybody's friendly if you don't bother
them okay including diamond mountain
stuff
okay
yes ma'am
[Music]
uh
yeah if you want to
you can add two extra things to the fire
at the end one is uh
if you did some bad stuff in the last
few months or lifetimes
you can
you can write it down
and offer it to the fire okay at the end
of the fire offering
just put some gasoline on it if it's too
big
uh and then uh
i like to throw in some money
uh
paper money because it it no i'm not
supposed to say that online
always follow the rules of your
government
but uh
okay anyway
it's a fun offering sometimes
because it's really sacrificing
something that you need
that you can use right okay
uh
what was the other thing
i don't remember
if i think of it all
yeah
today in the afternoon uh we're gonna
have a
you know i never cared much about my
weight
i was just you know
have good metabolism i'd like to eat
everything i can eat
but as i get older it's slowing down and
uh
so i i and i wanted to do a cleanse
for my kidneys and my liver and
so i asked anatol
who's the expert at this kind of stuff
he does it all the time
to give me a
a suggestion and then he wrote something
down
and uh i lost 15 pounds in the last
two weeks
how many kilos is that
[Music]
oh it's about seven kilos or something
like that and i feel really good and
light and my yoga is better and my
meditation's better i'm nicer person
[Music]
so people ask me if i could share
it
and so me and adriana are gonna
teach it to you
in the afternoon andrea
is that good
what time is that
um
two o'clock
okay
and oh can you bring some paper cups
also and we can share the
maybe we don't want them to taste it
uh
but uh then if you want to try it
sometime you can try it
huh
two o'clock
it's at the big front end of the
long-run class and we won't take the
whole class time just um sometime
good
okay
we have a plan to do it right here uh
julia child style
[Music]
you like those tv cooking shows
okay
she's gonna wear a mini skirt and an
apron
okay just the apron
i mean
all right
let's do some uh
ramen
or confession
thank you
actually this part of the alarm rim is
the
vows
the 12 vowels
of refuge so i taught them a little bit
in thailand
and
try to learn them today well
because then you can teach them to other
people okay so all of you
uh can give
vows to other people anybody in this
room
can give vowels refuge vows to other
people you don't have to be a monk or
none okay
you can give refugee vows
so it's a very sweet gift to give to
someone
and it's cool to give people a new name
it's like uh baptized over again you
know born again and you get a new name
and uh so you can do it anybody here can
do it
but i think it's nice to know the refuge
vows
and i don't give people refuge unless
they
heard the vows
correctly first
okay
so you should know the vows and uh you
shouldn't give refuge unless
uh you've explained the vows first okay
there's a bad custom in the world of
lamas giving
tantric initiations
to people they don't even know
it's supposed to be
a very close relationship between the
student and the teacher it binds them
together forever
it's like it's more serious than getting
married
so you should know the llama and the
llama should know you for many years
before they give you initiation
um
there's some like uh what do you call it
just kind of like good luck initiation
that's okay
give to 5000 people or something
like the color chakra
that's okay
uh
that's a different thing
that's called mendoke saban what's that
yeah plan an unstoppable state for the
future
they can get a real initiation okay so
that's okay
uh that's okay but
in general if if you take a
secret initiation or
you give one
uh you should explain the vowels okay
because
any
another initiation higher initiation
that you get
you have to take the vowels
whether you know about them or not okay
you get the vowels in the initiation
and then oftentimes the some teachers it
seems like they won't get they don't
teach the student the vows okay
and if you don't keep the balance you
you get terrible trouble
and if you keep them the talented
initiation works
uh and the vows are based on guess what
refuge
okay plain old morality
okay and being nice to other people okay
so
anyway
it's kind of weird
i heard of a llama someone met them in
the airport
some big llama and they were leaving on
a plane in 20 minutes and
they said will you give me refuge and
they like blah blah blah blah and gave
them a name and got on the plane
and that's not good okay you should
explain the vows
so anybody in this room and all the
centers singapore new york you can give
refugee mouse it's very sweet
and
but you should explain the vows before
you give them so don't do the ceremony
in a rush you know take two three hours
have a nice big
breakfast and explain the vows slowly
carefully answer all their questions
and then take refuge okay
good
like all practical battles you only have
to take them once in your life
and technically you cannot take them
again unless you lose them
but uh
sometimes for good luck i will give
people refuge vows
again just for good luck but technically
you you keep them your whole life you
can't lose them okay
all right here we go uh unless you
decide to give them up that's your
choice okay okay
here are the
rules here
doesn't mean trainings here lovejohn
means rules
uh for keeping for taking refuge
uh
then there are individual
rules and there are combined rules
anybody want to guess what that means
while i drink my coffee
what do you think
but what's it mean
oh think of the 12 refuge commitments
and give me a better answer
uh no
the
there's a set of refuge valves that are
particular to a different jewel this
one's for sangha jewel this one's for
damage on this one
and then there's refuge valves that
combine all the jewels okay here we go
number one
uh
dumbo knee
and these are uh if you notice the
refuge valves start off with negative
vowels don't do this don't do this don't
do this okay
then they go into positive valves okay
uh this is refuge round number one okay
uh once you have taken refuge in the
buddha jewel
don't take refuge in other useless
things
that's all
okay like
cell phone
okay
and that
for you guys taking refuge is going to
be harder
you know it
if if the student was not trained shun
chamola took a mana
if they don't have training in the great
teachings like nagarjuna or song
then you can say you know don't go to uh
baptist church if you're catholic or
something like that okay
and that's a
simple and low way to explain it you you
guys have a more serious responsibility
you have to try not to think of things
as coming from themselves like cell
phone doesn't work
from its own side cell phone works
because
you helped a couple
that was arguing or
you helped someone communicate with
their parents better
last week that's why your cell phone
works okay
you can drop your cell phone and it will
work
if you have the right seats i i dropped
my computer yesterday
boom
it's fine
uh
you know uh
okay it's
cell phone works if you help other
people to communicate okay
so your responsibility as
super well-trained refuge takers
is not is to try to not take refuge in
in things
okay
take refuge in doing good
okay the world is made of
kindness not atoms
okay that's our viewpoint okay so that's
that's the first foul once you take
refuge in the buddha
don't take lower refuges okay
it doesn't mean that you can't take
medicine
or
it doesn't mean that you can't go to a
marriage counselor or okay it doesn't it
doesn't mean that
yes sir
in the beautiful thank you for teaching
in the beautiful meditations we did just
now
we wanted to focus
what we wanted to achieve in maine
i realized that whatever popped into my
mind was a kind of refuge before
applying refuge to it yeah good so i'm
like when i'm going to refuge on wanting
this
stuff so
oh that's fine that's fine yeah
i mean the purpose of refuge is to get
all the things we want
and the books always say
neck up don tartu
the things we want i want a coffee this
morning
i want a certain kind of coffee errol
pressed
with one and a half the normal coffee
like we discussed it before i came to
class and uh
that's okay
you know this buddhist thing that you
should be unhappy
or you shouldn't go shopping or
starbucks is evil or you know
you know try to get over that
yeah it's fine cool thank you yeah want
things
then get them in a beautiful way
okay
uh
these buddha paradises they're not like
cement rooms with nose furniture
okay
got it
they're always like
there's coffee in there somewhere
these fruits here are the
sense objects okay
okay
all right
so he was referring to some a lot of
this book is cultural tibetan cultural
it doesn't apply directly to us but
maybe we can find something there okay
so in a buddhist monastery in tibet
uh
monks will uh
if they get a small problem they will
take refuge and try to use the four
steps
then if the problem gets more serious
they'll go
to fortune tellers and
you know
[Music]
get their what do you call fortune told
and
you know weird people i i saw it in the
monastery we have a
oracle
in our monastery we have a really good
and
people will go to this oracle one day i
was
asked to translate uh for the oracle he
he was the secretary of the monastery
he's very nerdy
i don't know like tim or something
you know and he's he's very you know
mild and happy guy and he's quiet he
works very nice and
he was the secretary
and then
you know once a month he'll do the
oracle thing and he goes to a special
temple small temple
and he wears a
whole
ancient
uh warriors
outfit
with a sword the real
thing and then he goes into trance you
know
and he's like
and you have to stay away from him
because he can actually hurt you
seriously
you have to just
you have to be in the room but you got
to watch
because sometimes he'll go crazy you
know and he hurts people you got to be
careful
and he's just controlled his like stuff
coming out
and uh
so uh i was asked to translate for this
canadian lady
you know and and i went in there and i
was like stay back okay
i'll stay between you and the guy
and they're all these monks there you
know
and then uh
she asked him uh she was looking she was
trying to
find a boyfriend or something
uh
so she came in and and we did this
you know we started the ritual
and it they're actually two three guys
hold him down
try to hold him down so he won't it
takes two three big guys
he's not a big guy but when he gets the
oracle inside of him he
you need
you know
so we started and and he was like
these guys are holding him you know and
he's got this thorn
and then he says i said okay ask a
question you know
and she says you know i'm really looking
for a partner in my life you know he's
like
he's like
okay
first decide what you want
number two
choose somebody else
number three
serve them at starbucks
number four do coffee man
she's like
okay okay
then he's like don't forget
study long
study learning
she's like okay okay i'll do it
you know then i'm like
it was so funny
then she's she was in the monastery for
like three weeks
listening to laura mim it wasn't enough
she wanted to hear it from oracle you
know so don't be like that okay
he says that some monks that get a
problem
they go to some weird guy and you know
oh tell me my future in china you guys
do it a lot you know it's a waste of
time
my llama said you want to know your
future check your six times book
[Music]
okay
anyway
okay temperature
and they bow down to these oracles you
know
tongue
adam you should still be marking stuff
for uh
the dictionary or online dictionary okay
so kang dong
kang means lake
chang means to pull
and it means a disgrace
it's the tibetan word for disgrace it's
the monastic word for disgrace you are
pulling down the legs of the sangha
it means you are disgraced you know
you you're a buddhist you understand
refuge you know the four steps you
should be at starbucks but you're in the
oracle's room
you should be at starbucks but you went
to the oracle instead understand
okay then that's a disgrace you know
somebody took a lot of dci courses and
then they
when they have a problem they run to a
fortune teller this is a disgrace okay
you should be embarrassed
okay
all right
means you are pulling down the leg of
the dharma people okay
so
when you
run to a fortune teller
and you split your refuge object right
you you say i have buddha dharma sangha
refuge object and i have a fortune
teller refuge object then you he says
you destroy your refuge bus
and then uh
nang bay telney
okay you should uh write that one adam
tell me uh g-r-a-l
[Music]
means uh
you just spit yourself out of the
buddhists
you know
okay you got kicked out of buddhist by
who
by you
okay
it's a tough word it's a kind of a rough
word uh
pl
you got kicked out you know uh by
yourself all right you split your refuge
on it
okay all right
on
uh
it's okay to make tormas
and offer them to local spirits it's not
like you're going for refuge right
so that's not
chitten means uh that's okay if you do
it with an understanding that the
the wind spirits are not gonna help you
if you don't have the seeds okay
okay but don't like put all your faith
in
local spirits okay
lou means
means local spirits
here it's deva but it means local
spirits lu means nagas
means like power power spirits of power
dorma you can offer that song
i've made a note here is to burn juniper
uh sore is uh
it's a kind of cheese torma okay
that's okay but capsicum be good but
don't take refuge in them don't put all
your hopes in some
local spirit okay
he just says it's inappropriate for
example to go to a government official
and pay them some money to try to get
something okay that's not real refuge
okay
paying a torma to making deals with
local spirits is not taking refuge okay
um
what is that
oh
a
i i looked up store it's a offering of
cheese and uh
it has what they call the three white
elements and the three red elements and
uh
i looked them up
the three white elephants are elephants
elements are yogurt milk and butter and
the three red ones i thought it was some
kind of tempting thing you know but it's
not i asked yeshi lotar on the phone
he said it's something like
honey
sugar
and
kuro means uh
what they call that in india
jaggery
it's a chunk of uh
brown sugar really tasty
that's one of the best cigarettes in the
world okay
all right
so i gotta fix this notes
[Music]
so it's not meat and blood
uh honey
sugar
and brown
sugar hunk
it's good for cooking indian cooking
what's that
really same thing
oh
korea
and you me what do you call that stuff
mole you use it in malay
yeah
you have to make me a monet something
show me your grandmother's secret recipe
real tantra
okay
all right um
i made a mistake on the notes here this
should say uh oh i corrected it yeah
that's weird
once you've taken refuge in the dharma
sanjayana nuteime
don't hurt anybody
including animals okay
girls say somebody snuck into the bottom
of the uh
compost thing
yeah they made a tunnel
just like that
gang guys in mexico
they broke into my compost
anyway
that will explain the watermelon rinds
around your whole neighborhood okay
uh chillicothe
i think i got them all okay
machine let's say young i also broke one
of your dishes i'm sorry
okay anyway i'm confessing
um then obviously i don't have to tell
you that it's wrong to to beat
living beings to hit living beings to
strike a living being
uh to kill a living being i don't have
to tell you that okay obviously you
can't be a meat-eater and keep this bow
okay obviously you can't be a meat-eater
and keep this about okay
uh
soap nope i thought
she
what we're going to talk about this
afternoon is they're just some things
that shouldn't be food that are foods
okay they shouldn't be foods like
shouldn't eat them
okay
we don't need people's meat
right
that would be weird right
i think 100 years from now they will say
we were really weird in these days you
know
the early american uh what do you call
these these very smart people like
george washington thomas jefferson
they kept slaves
human slaves
and then uh
if you ask them why you keep a slave
they will say not this is not a person
you know they believe that these big
enlightened guys
who made america
you know they believe that 100 years
later 200 years later we say oh my god
these guys were crazy you know that was
really ignorant
super stupid
extreme stupid
and then i think 100 years from now
people will look at us and say do you
can you imagine they used to
grow cows and kill them and
it was so weird
you know
uh okay
then yeah what about milk
uh my theory of milk is
they have to be kept pregnant to make
them melt
when they're kept pregnant they have
babies
if they have male babies they kill them
immediately because they can't make milk
there is a
places that where they take care of the
cows forever
you know there are places in the united
states in new york from new york state
where they will
take care of the cows they won't kill
them
and they'll take care of them i don't
know if it's nice to make them pregnant
all the time but
uh generally
when you're trying to decide whether
something is right or wrong see what
that food does to you
okay and i think like meat makes you
unhealthy okay
all right uh miyupi telgawa means
uh
inordinate tax a tax which is not fair
okay that's also hurting other people
not paying your taxes
okay it's hurting everybody
uh
dunder tower looked at me to be quiet
and to mistreat animals
okay
uh mengama tsun young no
so once you've taken refuge in the
dharma
we shouldn't
hurt animals either okay
[Music]
i'm gonna go for five more minutes and
we'll take a break so those of you with
pp
five more minutes
then you know a sign of successful
refuge is that you're nice to other
people okay
if you understand emptiness what's a
sign you understand emptiness do your
eyes go up in the top of your head
and sometimes you go like this
what's a sign you understand emptiness
you treat people nice
okay
okay you become much nicer
okay it's not some weird thing okay
all right
if people are empty they're coming from
you if they're coming from you they're
coming from your seeds if they're coming
from your seeds you should plant nice
seeds unless you like being around the
irritating people
got it
therefore people who understand
emptiness are just nice
and that's a sign of someone who
understands emptiness or who takes
refuge okay
all right negative vowel number three
relating to sangha
gendun capsules
once you take refuge in the sangha
as we said to elizabetha's question
try not to
if you have choice try to hang around
people
who understand
seeds okay that's all
try to hang around people who understand
things it doesn't mean
you should hate other people
it doesn't mean you can't talk to your
uncle if they don't understand things it
doesn't mean that
never use religion as an excuse to
dislike people okay
it's all
uh
you know
you should learn to fit in with people
that you're with
okay without you know doing bad things
but
you know
when you're with
normal guys you should talk about
football okay that's okay make them
comfortable
learn a little bit about football
okay
and
you know
make when you go to your family's
holidays then you can talk about
football that's okay
and don't don't use religion as an
excuse to dislike other people okay or
to say they're not us okay
but
uh people you hang around with day to
day
if they're
people who understand seeds then
they will keep you in the right track
okay
all right
then you should write that down adam it
then
i
it really when we when we write it is it
then when you say it it's like this
you know do you believe in buddha i mean
i ain't so sure you know
maybe yes maybe no you know
do you think the best way to fix an air
conditioner is to help other people with
fixing their stuff i i mean
you know
i am means
could be but i don't know
it's kind of weird
you know like
wishy-washy in english you know maybe
it's true maybe it's not okay
then he he says there's a very bad habit
in the
in tibet
where
somebody will come up and say uh
you know
my friend's looking for a partner okay
then you say okay i have a suggestion
what
my llama said they should go to the
nursing home and and visit lonely people
you know
and then this person
these are we we call reasonable devils
reasonable devils you know they'll say
what
and you say you know my mama said if you
want to find a partner and then go to
the nursing home and visit lonely people
you know and then they'll say
you know it sounds nice and
i understand that your llama wants you
to visit nursing homes it's probably
probably it's just a way to get you to
go to the nursing home you know it's
it's it's unreasonable
to believe that that would get you a
partner
okay
this kind of very
reasonable person
not like a
we say the devil comes that way
buddhism says the devil comes that way
you know you want to see a demon they're
not like
they're like
you know it sounds cool it's very sweet
i really respect your llama
it's it's a really nice thought it's
really sweet but you know
come on
you know
it's just he just wants you to go to the
nursing home
don't don't expect to get a partner
come on be reasonable
be practical
when someone says be practical you
should run away
that's a nice
demon
demon came
be proud don't look at ants all day what
are you thinking
you know be practical okay
minion d
d means uh
hang out with those people don't hang
out
closely with those people okay
all right uh one more
two more minutes
we are
not so
strong in our understanding of the seed
system we are not that strong we are
influenced by other people okay
my brother killed himself
uh
and
he went to hawaii because he was a
really good surfer
you know and i went to be with him
for a few months before he died
and we served some big ways
you know one day we broke both our
surfboards in half
on this wave and uh
but but he had some really weird friends
you know and they were doing drugs and
stealing things and
you know
and i thought uh
he's gonna something's gonna happen you
know these people are weird you know
it's not good for him
so
don't
you know be careful who you put around
you you know be careful who you hang out
with if someone has if you have a bad
habit
if you have a weakness like alcohol or
something
or anything
it's very common to
to find friends who support that habit
you know they'll say come on
you you're strong let's go have a drink
you know and
you're strong enough
it's not going to kill you you know and
then so be careful
getting close to people who have the
same weaknesses that you have okay
try to hang around people who are
stronger
if you want to lose weight hang out with
anatol
okay
don't hang out with someone who's gonna
give you chocolate bars all day okay
all right
okay
so our tendency is that if we stay close
to people who have the same bad habits
that we have
we will it will spread to us okay
dog
seem good keep them at a distance
keep them at a distance it doesn't mean
hate them it doesn't mean be unfriendly
to them
but
keep a little
personal space from them don't quite
buy into their view of the world
okay
so it's important to know how to keep a
distance and still be sweet and
and
friendly
but keep a little distance okay
all right
but do try to stay close to the bathroom
uh
so we'll take a break
10 15 minutes
okay see you at 9 45.
gashala the other day when we were
talking about buddhist images and you
mentioned that
there was one
very first one in some book i was
wondering if you
had the picture you could show us
yeah
uh
so i was
i've been really working hard on the
wheel of life because we we want to do a
book hector's helping with it and uh
so i've been reading all the old sutras
on the wheel of life vasubandhu wrote a
very beautiful long commentary and if
you know vasubandhu
he's most famous for
abhidhamma which he didn't believe in he
was asked to write it by his brother who
was
a sangha and he didn't believe it so
it's kind of
his style is cramped
but when he gets to the wheel of life
the 12 links uh
it's a long long commentary it took me
several months to finish it and um
it's awesome
it's unbelievable and you see vasa bandu
as a different person more like
a rock and roll guy
you know he's not this little i'll be
dharma you know
and uh
so sorry stanley
uh
he's doing the abu dhabi question uh but
anyway
uh i found several references that say
that the first
uh rendering of the buddha
in this world was the wheel of life
so the buddha which is now up in the
corner of the wheel of life in those
days
the main image was lord buddha
and the wheel was a little tiny piece on
the painting so uh
you know by tradition that's the very
first
uh image of the wheel of life and um
sorry the first image of the buddha in
this world
i don't know how similar the current
paintings of the buddha in the wheel of
life are to the
historical buddha
and we're working on that
we're working on finding some early
paintings
two more things
according to those sources the first
written buddhist books are the wheel of
life
the two verses at the bottom
are are the first thing that the buddha
wrote down
you see because he was an oral teacher
and so that's some of the first written
british teachings are also on the wheel
of life
and
some of the earliest uh
statute statuary of the buddha is
gandharvan which is the custom
of the buddhists of afghanistan
and pakistan and schweinstein
walked through those areas on his way to
india and
those are interesting uh buddhas because
they look more like western people
and the earliest statue i've seen of
vajrapani looks like winston churchill
or something
so it just makes you aware that uh
how people
paint the buddha or
or jesus they usually
when the british
were the world's power they painted
jesus like a british man
but he was a dark-skinned
you know
jew right in is in in the middle east he
he probably had a big nose and black
hair and and he was strong because he
was a carpenter so you know
it just different people paint
the buddha in their own image and i i
don't think it's so bad i think maybe
it's okay
there is a tradition in tibet uh
of
and there are ancient scriptures about
the correct uh dimensions
like from here to here and here to here
and
and that's why tibetan painters
will paint that uh
grid
because there's rules about
to make it correct
but i think
in modern times it would be interesting
to
interpret the buddhist face
and
so we're doing a we're doing a paperback
version of this big red book
so people can afford it
and
i'm going to send scott
to nick
i'll send you the picture of the of
tonka
what's the internet here scott
oh boy oh you don't want to tell
everybody
i'll give it to you on a flash drive
now i'll give it to you okay a flash
drive
yeah but that's too complicated for me
oh people over 40.
you want to just drop it to yourself
here
[Music]
sorry
so where is the earliest rendering of
the wheel of life with buddhist people
oh no that's a question so we're working
on that
thank you very much our team our german
team
uh sylvia engelhardt
she's found 600 paintings so far
and
i haven't gone through them yet uh
well please share when you do thank you
yeah i wanna have some time
here it is
okay
i think it's really high risk
anyway we're playing around with new
images of lord buddha
and son kapa i'll show you one
uh okay any other question
mr
joel happy birth oh that's yesterday
thank you yeshua and thanks everybody um
just a question about
how to deal with and plant seeds with
the reasonable devils that you mentioned
you know
uh
we talked about reasonable devils it
means uh people who say you know i
understand you went to a retreat and
you're all excited about it but just
calm down you know
you can't run your life that way
you have responsibilities you know
you can't
you can't do all that you know uh so how
do you deal with those people
i can give you normal advice which is
devil advice
or uh
i can give you uh like the diamond
cutter sutra i was this morning
i i came down here at five and worked on
the internet and um
i was thinking what to call the kamala
sheila course and in the diamond cutter
sutra
that we're going to cover this course
the student what's his name
so booty
he starts crying
in the middle of the sutra he starts
crying
and
i thought it was so beautiful i thought
to call the course arya's tears the
tears of an arya because it says there's
an expression
it's called the tears of the arya and
they talk about that
in the sutra
the tears of the arya and then
somebody asked him why he's crying
and he says
there's nothing reasonable in this whole
sutra i like it
you mean there's no normal advice
you know it's not like
uh
you know
try to be nice to them or uh maybe
change your hairstyle or you know
there's nothing like that every single
verse
buddha says what he really wants to say
which is
use the four steps use the four steps
use the word he doesn't say anything but
emptiness no there's not one normal
advice in the whole sutra
so
fix them you know which means
uh try to catch yourself being
reasonable
because they're coming from you so
you have a small tendency somewhere
inside of you like a vein running
through a stone
there's a small tendency somewhere
to think that all this is not very
practical
and then uh attack that and they will
change
see then you don't have to change your
relationship with them they will just
slowly change to being
friends who talk about seeds all the
time
okay cool that's the real answer
then lesser you know hinayana answer
would be
you know
try to move closer to tina's uh house
and you know
stuff like that you can do that also
you ready
thank you guessa you're welcome
we're playing with something like that
i don't know
but what i mean is uh
maybe we can
change
what we
think is a buddhist painting
you know
maybe we can
paint the buddha in many different ways
that's by uh
my godson actually
okay
all right one more question i think
hi geshla hi thank you so much for this
opportunity
thank you for coming
um earlier when you talked about
surrounding ourselves with those who um
or not to surround ourselves with those
who have the same bad habits or
weaknesses as we do
what if we do surround ourselves with
those the same have bad habits and
weaknesses are we helping them
serving them by helping ourselves too to
remove those bad habits as well
yeah that's why he said
that's why he said
just the last sentence he said
means
us guys
sam means our mind demba means
well established in our worldview
well established in our worldview so if
you can hold on to it
and hang out with your old friends
that's okay because then you're helping
them so that's best if you can do it but
be uh
reasonable
about how much you can do
you know like don't uh
i keep thinking about alcoholics you
know they they tend to
look for friends or people who can't
stop using drugs they tend to
make friends with people that are using
drugs and after they become buddhist
they say
i'm going to fix them you know
then they go out with their friends and
they end up doing drugs you see what i
mean so
just be honest with yourself about
how much you can
how strong you can be if you can be
strong and affect them that's best
yeah that's best
thank you so much
okay
okay let's
do yoga
maybe
oh what's next
you john
right not yo tao yoga
your hearing is
something
yeah is it next yes
she said oh yeah
[Music]
okay
thank you for being so sweet it's a
really unusually sweet group and it's
i enjoy it i enjoyed going deeper
all right